Guide to the John Augustus Hartwell Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
John Augustus Hartwell papers
1913-1933
MS 1340
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.5
Chiefly papers documenting John Augustus Hartwell's activities as a Yale alumnus, particularly on behalf of the Yale University Athletic Association. Included are correspondence, articles of incorporation, minutes and reports of the Association. Other papers concern the class of 1889, Yale-in-China, and Hartwell's service as a major in the Medical Corps during World War I.
Hartwell, J. A. (John Augustus), 1869-1940
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mrs. John A. Hartwell, 1941.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The John A. Hartwell Papers consist of correspondence, minutes, and other material related to Hartwell's activities as an active, dedicated, and generous alumnus of Yale University. Hartwell served on the Board of Control of the Yale University Athletic Association from 1916-1917, and almost half of the material in the papers documents his interest in athletic facilities, health standards for athletes, and other aspects of the sports program. Most of the correspondence is routine, but there are letters in folder 3 which express the attitudes of Yale students and administrators to World War I. Of note also are the fund raising letters of William S. ("Shriver") Clawson and Hartwell's interesting response during the Depression in folder 4.
Biographical / Historical
John Augustus Hartwell, Ph.B. 1889.
Born September 27, 1869, in Sussex, N.J.
Died November 30, 1940, in Oakdale, N.Y.
Father, Samuel Slawson Hartwell (B.A. 1859). Mother, Mary Clarinda (Stiles) Hartwell. Yale relatives include an uncle, William A. Stiles (B.A. 1859).
Sedgwick School, Great Barrington, Mass. Biology course at Yale; prize for excellence in all studies and for excellence in physics Freshman year; Senior appointment and honorable mention Belknap Natural History Prize; Class crew Freshman and Junior years; Universtiy Crew four years and captain 1891-92; on University Football Team four years; vice-president Yale University Boat Club Senior year; Class president Junior year; second vice-president Y.M.C.A. Senior year; member The Colony and Berzelius; Ph.B. 1889. Enrolled as graduate student Sheffield Scientific School 1889-90 (assistant in physiological chemistry) and Yale School of Medicine 1890-92 (M.D. cum laude 1892).
Graduate student College of Physicians and Surgeons, Columbia University, 1892-93; interne [ sic] Presbyterian Hospital 1894-97; physician and surgeon New York City 1897-1940 (retired from active surgical work 1933); consulting surgeon New York, Bellevue, Presbyterian, Lincoln, Reconstruction, and Memorial hospitals, New York infirmary for Women and Children, Lawrence Hospital (Bronxville), and United Hospital (Port Chester); instructor in physiology Cornell University Medical College 1898-99; instructor in physiology and assistant demonstrator in anatomy 1900-01; assistant professor of physiology 1902-03; professor of clinical surgery 1909-10, 1911-12, 1918-19, and 1932-33; assistant professor of surgery 1911-12 and associate professor 1918-19; professor of surgery emeritus 1939; a frequent contributor to medical journals; commissioned Major, Medical Corps, January 26, 1918; director of instruction in war surgery Bellevue Hospital; overseas August 1-November 20, 1918; detached service with A.E.F. in connection with medical supplies furnished by American Red Cross; later assigned to surgeon-in-chief, 1st Army, Souilly; served with evacuation and field hospitals during part of Meuse-Argonne offensive; consultant surgeon Debarkation Hospital, Port of New York, until honorable discharge July 1, 1919; vice-president New York Academy of Medicine 1918-20, president 1929-33, director 1934-39, trustee 1928, 1933-34, and 1939-40; secretary and treasurer New York Surgical Society 1905-07, president 1921-23; president Society of Clinical Surgery 1928, 1933; associate director American Society for the Control of Cancer 1939-40; fellow American College of Surgeons; member medical societies of County and State of New York, American Association for Thoracic Surgery, National Tuberculosis Association, American Medical and Surgical associations, American Association for the Advancement of Science, and International Surgical Society; director and member executive committee More Game Birds in America, Inc., 1930-40; trustee Ducks Unlimited 1937-40 (first president 1937-38); president Association of Yale Alumni in Medicine 1937-38; graduate member Yale University Athletic Association and Board of Control; on medical advisory committee Yale-in-China; member Century, Links, and Southside Sportsman's clubs, University Club, Yale Club of New York, and St. James' Church (Episcopal), New York City.
Married April 16, 1910, in Port Chester, N.Y., Mary Butler Green Fulton, daughter of Albert William and Mary Thompson (Butler) Green. No children.
Death due to acute coronary occlusion. Buried in Green-Wood Cemetery, Brooklyn, N.Y. Survived by wife and two sisters, Mrs. Emma H. McCully and Miss Louise Hartwell, both of Montclair, N.J.
(Taken from Yale Obituary Record, 1941, pages 179-181).
Armed Forces; World War, 1914-1918; Physicians; Soldiers; Hartwell, J. A. (John Augustus), 1869-1940; Yale College (1887- ). Class of 1889; Yale University Athletic Association; Yale University -- Sports; Yale University -- Students; Yale-China Association
- Inventory
  - Berzelius Society (The Colony): correspondence, 1919-1933 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Chittenden (Russell H.) Fund: correspondence, 1913-1921 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - World War I, Hartwell's service and Yale Batteries: correspondence and related material, 1916-1919, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Yale Alumni University Fund Association: correspondence, 1914-1933 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Yale Club: correspondence, 1918-1932 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Yale Club, Committee on Scholarships: correspondence, 1922-1923 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Yale in China: correspondence, 1916-1920 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Yale Medical Alumni Association: correspondence, 1921-1932 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Yale University Athletic Association: correspondence
    - A-B, 1916-1931 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - C, 1915-1919 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - D-F, 1915-1918 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - G-H, 1915-1919 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - J-M, 1915-1928 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - N, R-T, 1915-1928 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - W-Y, 1915-1918 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Minutes, reports, articles of incorporation, 1916-1919 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Board of Control: minutes and correspondence, 1916-1920 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Yale University Athletics: correspondence (President Angell, Comptroller Farnum), 1931 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Yale University Class of 1889-Sheffield: correspondence, 1919-1926 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Yale University Endowment Fund: correspondence, 1927-1930 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Yale "1492" Dinner: correspondence, draft of speech, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Yale University Press: correspondence, brochures, 1916-1930 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1915-1932 (Box 1, Folder 23)